Okay טוב. tov. So yesterday we did two very important things. We
began a lot of important things. Number one is we established the
levels of negligence required or lack thereof required for liability for an
אדם המזיק. Adam HaMazik. נזק Nezek seemed to be in the גמרא
Gemara even if you're אונס, ones, have absolutely no negligence. The other
payments of צער, Tzar, נזק, Nezek, and ריפוי Reepuy of the חבלה
Chavala for personal injury, you needed to be negligent. רוח מצויה Ruach
Metzuyah said the גמרא, Gemara, but you didn't need to have כוונה.
kavana. And בושת, Boshet, you needed to actually have intention, intention not
necessarily to cause embarrassment, but intention to be מזיק. mazik. So that's
very important in terms of the base level of fault needed for
אדם המזיק. Adam HaMazik. But then we began the סוגיא sugya yesterday,
the new פרק, perek, that spoke about that if you break a
pitcher in רשות הרבים, Reshus HaRabim, you
would—and you're a person, you're an אדם המזיק—you Adam HaMazik would be
exempt if we assume that אין דרכן של בני אדם להסתכל בדרכים,
ein darkan shel bnei adam lehistakel badrachim, people don't normally look where
they're going. So it is, you know, there's a debate whether we
say people normally or don't normally look where they're going. If they
do normally look where they're going, then it would have to be
a special case like nighttime or whatever. But in circumstances in which
it's either not the norm for you to be watching out or
not normal for you to be—or somehow circumstances don't allow you to
watch out, you're exempt if you break something in רשות הרבים. Reshus
HaRabim. So whatever happened to אדם מועד לעולם, Adam Muad Le'olam, right?
That seems like a direct contradiction to what we talked and it
leads to two important positions in the ראשונים. Rishonim. תוספות Tosafot says
we say אדם Adam is מועד לעולם, Muad Le'olam, we don't really
mean it. We really mean that you don't need full negligence, but
you still certainly need a certain degree of negligence and if you're
a total אונס ones you're exempt. That's what תוספות Tosafot says. And
רמב"ן, Ramban, who says no, אדם Adam is מועד לעולם, Muad Le'olam,
but if you're stepping on somebody's pitcher in רשות הרבים Reshus HaRabim
and they know that people don't look where they're going, then they
shouldn't have put their pitcher in רשות הרבים Reshus HaRabim to begin
with. So when it's contributory negligence, פשיעת הניזק, peshiat hanizak, then that's
why you're exempt. So the issue about whether you normally watch where
you're going is not to establish that you had the basic—the minimum
level of negligence required. We don't need you to have any negligence.
It's to establish that this person was negligent by putting it there
because they should have been aware that they were asking for trouble
because you don't normally watch where you're going. Okay, so that's very,
very important in terms of אדם מועד לעולם. Adam Muad Le'olam. According
to תוספות, Tosafot, ושמואל אמר, v'Shmuel amar, תוספות Tosafot says that actually
you do need a certain degree of negligence and רמב"ן Ramban says
you do not but פשיעת הניזק peshiat hanizak exempts you. Now the
גמרא—now Gemara we turn to a critical discussion in the גמרא Gemara
which has broad ramifications, which is a discussion of עביד אינש דינא
לנפשיה. avid inish dina lenafshei. Can a person take the law into
his own hands? We'll see in a minute why this is being
brought up. It has to do with how we interpreted the משנה
mishna earlier, but the basic question was somebody was drawing water from
a well on a day that wasn't his, there was take times
of taking turns on a well, and the other guy hit him
with the shovel. And the question was what type of a fine
should that person pay for hitting him with a shovel? And the
answer was that he shouldn't have to pay any fine. רב נחמן
Rav Nachman said he shouldn't have to pay any fine because he
could be עביד אינש דינא לנפשיה. avid inish dina lenafshei. He was
protecting his own interests and he was taking the law into his
own hands. And even if we say a person normally is not
allowed to take the law into their own hands, they are במקום
פסידא, b'makom pseda, they are when they are about to—when they would
suffer a loss if they would wait to call the cops. Okay,
so if you wait to call the cops and you can completely
recover the loss, that's a debate then: can you take the law
into your own hands right now? But if you know that there
will be a definite loss without doing something now, everybody says you
can take the law into your own hands. So let's take a
look. So now we are going to enter into that discussion. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says like
this.
דאיתמר, de'itmar, we'll start. רב יהודה אמר, Rav Yehuda amar, it's the
line starts with the word אמר. amar. It is about 11 lines
from the bottom. Two אמר, amars, it's the first one. רב יהודה
אמר: Rav Yehuda amar: לא עביד אינש דינא לנפשיה. lo avid inish
dina lenafshei. A person is not allowed to take the law into
their own hands. רב נחמן אמר: Rav Nachman amar: עביד אינש דינא
לנפשיה. avid inish dina lenafshei. You are allowed to take the law
into your own hands. היכא דאיכא פסידא, heicha de'ika pseda, now the
גמרא Gemara repeats, if there's a loss, if you're going to wait
to call the cops, suffer the loss, try to recoup it in
court, כולי עלמא לא פליגי דעביד אינש דינא לנפשיה. kulei alma lo
pligi de'avid inish dina lenafshei. Nobody would—nobody would argue that you could
go ahead and take the law into your own hands.
כי פליגי היכא דליכא פסידא, ki pligi heicha de'leika pseda, when there's
no loss. רב יהודה אמר לא עביד אינש דינא לנפשיה דכיון דליכא
פסידא ליזיל קמיה דיינא, Rav Yehuda amar lo avid inish dina lenafshei
de'keivan de'leika pseda leizil kamei dayana, go to the courts, go to
the בית דין. Beis Din. רב נחמן אמר עביד אינש דינא לנפשיה
דכיון דבדין עביד לא טרח, Rav Nachman amar avid inish dina lenafshei
de'keivan de'bedin aveid lo tarach, since you're acting properly, you're just protecting
your own property, לא טרח, lo tarach, we don't make you go
through that effort. And of course what's also interesting is what about
the loss in terms of the court costs? What about the loss
in terms of the loss of time from your work in order
to argue the case? Right? But that seems to be—no, that's exactly
what they're debating. Do you need to go through that effort that
it takes to actually argue the case in court or is that
enough of a reason? why should I need to have to go
fight it in court I'm protecting my own interest? Okay. Now there
is you know let's read the סוגיא sugya first and then we'll
discuss like what some of the logic is behind why you should
be allowed versus you know why you shouldn't be allowed. Let's take
a look at some of the cases. Okay. מתיב רב כהנא, mativ
Rav Kahana, so Rav Kahana asks. בן בג בג אומר, Ben Bag
Bag omer, Ben Bag Bag says: אל תיכנס לחצר חברך ליטול את
שלך שלא ברשות. al tikanes l'chatzer chaveircha litol et shelcha shelo birshut.
Do not go in, you know that somebody has stolen your object
or is refusing to return your object, don't try to sneak into
his house to steal it back, okay, without permission. שמא תראה עליו
כגנב, shema tera'eh alav k'ganav, maybe you'll appear like a thief. You
know, and does that mean that it's about appearances? Does that mean
that you'll yourself sort of train yourself, you know, with these habits
of being a thief? But it's not proper in terms of your
own מדות middot and in terms of your perception in the community
and how and so on to go ahead and act in this
type of deceiving deceitful thieving way. So even though you're acting justly,
don't sort of steal into his place to retrieve it. Okay.
אלא, ela, rather שבור שיניו, shvor shinav, if you do it, do
it honestly, break his teeth, give him a, you know, exactly, you
know well sock him in the face ואמור לו שלי אני נוטל.
v'emor lo sheli ani notel. You know, don't go in the middle
of the night and try to sneak in. Knock on the door,
punch him out, and walk in straight. Okay. So anyway you see
עביד איניש דינא לנפשיה. avid inish dina l'nafsheh. You're not allowed to
do it in a way that's about thieving and whatever, that's obviously
deceitful and all those other things. But if you're clear about what
you're doing, you're coming to retrieve your property, you're allowed you're allowed
to, take the even if using force, which is pretty interesting. So
אמר ליה, amar leh, so he said back to him: אימא בן
בג בג יחידאה הוא. eima Ben Bag Bag yechida'ah hu. Yeah fine,
you have Ben Bag Bag on your side. He's a single opinion,
he's a minority opinion, ופליגי רבנן עליה. u'pligi rabanan aleh. I believe
that the rabbis argue on him. It doesn't show that the rabbis
argue on him, but I'm going to assume that the rabbis argue
on him. Okay. Now so by the way all the questions of
עביד איניש דינא לנפשיה avid inish dina l'nafsheh are ones in which
the other side is somehow suffering as a result. You're causing injury
to their person, to their object, and so on, okay, because otherwise
if the other side isn't suffering as a result, right? I mean
like if let's say you stole my wallet and you're sitting here
at the table and you turn your face and my wallet's right
there, I'm going to right should be able to take it right
back, it's my wallet, right? So the problem is that there's I'm
doing something that's in violation. If it's just the act of retrieving
my object and it's my object, then of course I'm allowed to
take my object. Okay, but the point is that there's some other
thing that I am violating in the process of trying to get
it. I'm trespassing, I'm punching you in the face, I'm taking you
know I'm damaging your property and so on. Okay, so anyway this
idea here that you're punch the guy in the face by the
way the first two cases
where you can just go take it back and I'm not going
to say
you can't go into the guy's house and steal it back. You
can't steal it back, that's because then you're acting in a thieving
way. But if you're honest and straightforward about it, you can punch
the guy out. Okay, so in two cases now we have you
using force. Hitting the guy with the shovel and punching the guy
in the face and we're going to allow the actual use of
force for you to protect your property. Okay, what we won't allow
is this like thieving deceitful type of an approach. All right, yes.
How about the damage caused to that other person? Like today we
have guns. You know, somebody says I'm going to take it and
he shoots the guy. Right, right.
Yeah, so I think that that's a real good question. Meaning that's
why I'm pointing it out because you might you and I might
have said maybe עביד איניש דינא לנפשיה avid inish dina l'nafsheh if
it's I don't know if you have to cause damage to the
person's property, but damage actually the person, like personal damage? And how
far does that go? Right. So that's exactly what I wanted to
put out there that that's a big חידוש. chiddush. Exactly. What?
Like a broken nose or broken teeth?
Yeah, broken teeth? שיניו, shinav, teeth? Right, exactly. Exactly. So I think
that's a very big חידוש. chiddush. Like it's one thing to say
you could do it, you know, and maybe even damage the person's
property in the process, but damage the person's person? And how far
would you take that? Okay. So let's take I mean are all
these things because they're because they're like because they're like not permanent
damage? I mean is
שבור שיניו shvor shinav depends if that's figurative, right? If it means
knock him out or does it literally mean knock out his teeth?
So okay so let's take a look. Okay, רב יינאי אמר, Rav
Yannai amar, so Rav Yannai says: No, I'm going even try to
get Ben Bag Bag to not be saying that this idea that
you can actually use
force... will get to עבד כנעני eved Kena'ani in a minute. Okay,
I don't know, yes. Anyway, רב יינאי אמר: Rav Yannai amar: מאי
שבור שיניו? mai shvor shinav? What does it mean break his teeth?
בדין. b'din. No, he doesn't Ben Bag Bag doesn't literally mean knock
him out. It means drag him into court. אי הכי, ei hachi,
if so, ואמור לו, v'emor lo, say to him I'm retrieving my
object, לא מיבעיא, lo miba'aya, it should be the court says to
him שלי אני נוטל, sheli ani notel, it shouldn't be I take
my object, שלו הוא נוטל, shelo hu notel, we're retrieving his object
מיבעיא ליה למימר miba'aya leh l'meimar should have said. קשיא. kashya. Okay,
that's difficult because it's obviously not what Ben Bag Bag said. Okay,
תא שמע. ta shema. Anyway so you got Ben Bag Bag that
says punch him out. Okay, come in here. And that was a
case of ליכא פסידא, leika psida, right? There was no evidence there
that if the object was staying in that guy's yard you were
losing money. is assault, you just did it in order so you
didn't have why should I bother going to court? Okay, תא שמע,
ta shma, come in here. שור שעלה גבי חבירו להורגו, Shor she'alah
gabei chaveiro lehorgo, an ox goes on top of another ox in
the attempt to kill the bottom ox. ובא בעל התחתון, u-va ba'al
hatachton, so the owner of the bottom ox doesn't want his ox
to get killed, ושמט את שלו, v'shamat et shelo, he pulls his
ox out from
below, ונפל העליון ומת, v'nafal ha'elyon u-met, and the top one fell
and died. פטור, patur, he's exempt from damages because he was just
protecting
his
own object. So מאי לאו mai lav במועד דליכא פסידא, be'mu'ad d'leika
psida, presumably we're talking even if the top ox is a מועד.
mu'ad. So you could totally recover, right, the difference, מועד mu'ad is
you get full damages, תם tam you get half, right? So you
could totally recover your full damages in court and even though you'd
be able to fully recover your damages in court you don't have
to wait to court and you can go ahead and protect your
own object, you know, even though it is you're going to cause
damage to the other person's property. So the גמרא Gemara says so
you see you're allowed to עביד איניש דינא לנפשיה. avid inish dina
l'nafsheih. לא, lo, בתם דאיכא פסידא. be'tam d'ika psida. No, we're talking
about a case of a תם tam where there is a loss
and that's why you're allowed to do it because you'd only recover
half. אי הכי אימא סיפא, ei hachi eima seifa, so let's look
at the end of that
ברייתא. braita. דחפו לעליון ומת, dechaf'o l'elyon u-met, if you pushed the
top one off, חייב, chayav, then you are חייב chayav because that
is considered, well we'll ask why in a minute, but that's different
than pulling out your own. ואי בתם, v'ei b'tam, if it's a
case of a תם, tam, אמאי חייב, amai chayav, why are you
חייב? chayav? Meaning the גמרא Gemara assumes if it was the way
תוספות Tosafot explains is that if it was a מועד mu'ad and
you were going to get your full recovery then you were able
to be a little calmer about it because at the back of
your mind you know even if I don't save my animal I'll
be able to recover damages, so then we could demand from you,
don't directly push his animal off, just take your animal from below.
But if it's a case of a תם tam where you're really
going to lose half of the damage then you're very anxious, right,
you're very rushed, you're really trying to save some permanent loss that
you might incur. So the גמרא Gemara assumes wait is it really
meaningful, is it really like feasible to ask him to only pull
out his animal rather than to push the top one? Why are
we making this distinction? And the גמרא Gemara says yes, even so
it is, שהיה לו לשמטו ולא שמטו, she'hayah lo l'shamto v'lo shamto,
because you should have yes, even in that case, even though you're
anxious because of a loss you might suffer a loss, we tell
you, you should have pulled the bottom one out rather than pushed
the top one off. Now let's pause for a moment. Why does
it matter? At the end of the day you are protecting your
property, you are עביד איניש דינא לנפשיה. avid inish dina l'nafsheih. Like
why is there this difference? You know, what the,
and let me ask this other question. Are we presuming that if
you pulled the bottom one out it would have the top would
have suffered less damage? Is the reason because when you push the
top one off you're doing more damage than necessary? So the idea
of עביד איניש דינא לנפשיה avid inish dina l'nafsheih is that you're
only allowed to do the absolute minimum amount of necessary damage in
order to achieve your goals? Okay, that's one way of understanding it,
yes.
And I thought the question of עביד איניש דינא לנפשיה avid inish
dina l'nafsheih was essentially once something has been committed can you go
ahead and take the money yourself so you don't have to wait
to go to בית דין? Beit Din? And then there'd be some
loss in between or maybe something.
Well that's an איכא פסידא ika psida scenario, right.
Right, if there were a loss in between. But whereas this is
a case where you're actually affecting the מציאות, metziut, you're affecting the
case itself and you're affecting its outcome. So can you intervene so
that you, I mean I think it's more questionable. Can you intervene
so that you minimize your own loss or your own outcome? Right.
Well I'm not understanding how is this different than the case of
the guy taking the water when it's not his day? He's going
to take the water and I'm going to suffer a loss because
my plants won't get watered or whatever and I'm trying to prevent
that case from happening. I mean you're right, there's types of עביד
איניש דינא לנפשיה avid inish dina l'nafsheih where I'm trying to prevent
myself from suffering the loss in the first place and there's a
time when I'm trying to recover something because the lack of recovering
it will cause a loss. Right, but so so far we've had
both, like the case of the well was preventing and the case
of this was the recovery. But anyway, but your point is if
you're trying to prevent it then you think you should have more
license or less license? Probably less.
I mean because you're setting up the damages, you're setting up the,
and so maybe you can only intervene in that case with your
own שור, shor, not someone else's.
Uh-huh.
So yeah, there are preemptive cases but this case is, seems to
me different in the sense that there's no guarantee that the above
ox is going to fall and get hurt. Right. In the other
case you're hitting the guy. Right. And you're clearly doing something. Here
you're doing something that should be within your right to protect your
own property preemptively or not, the ox is on top, but there's
no guarantee that's going to happen.
Right. So I think that that's, I mean I think that those
are the questions to ask, meaning is the difference between the top,
you could say the difference between the top and the bottom is
that the top is going to cause more damage and you have
to try to minimize the damage? Then you have to ask when
I'm knocking out a... I mean when he says, when before he
said like let him hit him a hundred times with a shovel,
right, doesn't sound like you have to like be so hyper-precise about
exactly the minimum amount that I need to. do to achieve it.
It does seem like the difference is more how, not because it's
likely to cause more damage, but how we frame what you're doing,
right, is what you're doing protecting your property or is what you're
doing actually seen as
like somehow damaging the other person's
property? So in most cases you can't draw the line. Like if
I gotta knock your face in in order to get into your
house, or hit you, right, there was no alternative. But here there's
an alternative. It's like if you were just protecting your property, you
would have seized your ox. So the fact that you're doing the
act on some other thing makes it less that you're protecting your
own thing. But it's still hard to see why that should make
such a difference.
What they're doing they're making a distinction between not having to go
through a טירחא, tircha, go to court to recoup your money. But
here they're saying if the ox is a מועד muad and you
know you're going to get your money back anyway, then you probably
don't have the right to do that without the whole טירחא tircha
of having to go replace your ox.
Well, that's the point but that's the issue. The issue is, is
the טירחא tircha of having to be without my ox, wait to
recover it in court, fight it in court, all those things. Now
if the טירחא, tircha, if the reality was that with the absence
of my ox I'm not going to get my field plowed, that
would be איכא פסידא. ikka p'seida. But if the only problem is
that I have to spend all that time in court, that seems
to be exactly the debate. Now what it's worth doing is now
is pausing anyway. So to get back, to get back, the point
is that look, the Gemara presumably since it phrases it as היה
לו לשמטו, haya lo lishamto, presumably would mean in a scenario where
it was not reasonable where you needed to push off the top
ox or it wasn't reasonable to try to focus on the bottom
one, then of course you'd be entitled. That's like I gotta punch
the guy's face in to get to it. But when it really
was feasible to grab the bottom one then pushing the top makes
it that I'm not just doing an act of protecting my property,
redefines the nature of the act seems to be. Let's take a
minute though and appreciate what seems to be being laid out here
as the justification for עביד איניש דינא לנפשיה. avid inish dina lenafshei.
What seems to be the justification for עביד איניש דינא לנפשיה avid
inish dina lenafshei is your right
to protect your property, right? It's sort of
like if you're coming to steal from me,
the whole case of בא במחתרת. ba bemachteres. Somebody's coming to tunnel
in to steal from me, right I'm allowed to stand up to-
why don't we say, oh well if I stand up to him
he's going to be trying to kill me and then I'll make
him into a רודף rodef and then I'm allowed to kill him.
I don't understand. Why don't I just let him take my property?
Why should I turn the whole case into a case that he's
going to now try to kill me? So the point is it
starts from a position that you have the right to protect your
property and to actually use force. Let's say you're coming at me,
right, and you're coming to steal my thing. Am I allowed to
punch you to stop you from stealing my thing? We don't say
יכול להציל באחד מאיבריו yachol l'hatzil b'echad m'eivarav if you're taking- no
I'm allowed to use force to stop you from stealing from me,
right? So if we start with that assumption, if I need to
use force I'm allowed to. So here the question is let's just
view it as the same thing. You've got my object, right, your
continued holding of my object means you're continuing to steal my property
and I'm just using force to protect my property. That's a way
of looking at it, particularly if it's איכא פסידא. ikka p'seida. If
I'm actually losing money as a result of it, right, then I'm
just trying to protect myself. And that could be the question, how
much am I really- is it continued when there's no direct monetary
loss but the loss of taking the case to the court, or
just the reality that you're holding onto my property is itself seen
as an act of I'm just protecting what is mine. You don't
buy it.
Off track, but just to muddy the water, one presumes this is
happening in רשות הרבים? rishus harabim?
It's not clear. שדה חבירו. s'deh chavero.
If you're walking down a רשות הרבים rishus harabim how come I've
got pots all over the place and you're about to step on
one of my pots, so I push you out of the way?
No but that's פשיעת הניזק psiyat hanizak also. I mean then do
you have a right to do that if you were to blame
for what was about to happen? I mean that's raising a separate
question.
I've got my pots all- I thought we determined that you really
can't put your pots all over the place if it's someone else's
progress.
You can't. But we're going to get to that case in a
minute.
My question is in the case of the shovel, right? So I
take your wallet, you know, then it's fine. So then you're coming
in with the, whatever it is, to try to beat me to
get it back. So I see you bearing down with the shovel
and then I punch you because I don't want to be hit
by the shovel, right? So am I- am I חייב chayav now?
Right so that's- I'm defending myself against you trying to take it
back.
Yeah that is a very good question. You're right, we haven't dealt
with that. If the guy tries to fight back, right, what's his
liability? That's a good question.
It's definitely discussed. I don't know the answer off the top of
my head but it's definitely discussed. But I want to say so
that's why as both of you have pointed out, we're dealing with
two cases. One is preventing damage and one is recouping property, right?
But and the fact that we're looking at it all the same
might point us to the idea that עביד איניש דינא לנפשיה avid
inish dina lenafshei is conceptually the idea of using force to protect
your own property and does that apply if there's
no- not dealing with a specific concrete object that the other person
has. Let's say you went ahead and you borrowed $100 from me
and then you're lying and you're never returning it. Can I go
ahead and steal into, go into your house and take $100 out
of your wallet? Okay, so would that be עביד איניש דינא לנפשיה?
avid inish dina l'nafsheih? And he says you're absolutely not allowed to
do it. Now the reason he says you're not allowed to do
it is he basically says that then that'll lead to a complete
falling apart of the social fabric here, you're completely undermining it because
everybody's stealing from everybody else and saying they're coming to recover some
type of a loss. But besides that, the point is that the
conceptual idea that it's my property that you are destroying and taking
and seizing, right? So here the property's already been taken and it's
no longer in existence. It's money, it's been used and so on.
I want to now get paid back, compensation, not protecting my property,
but compensation. Compensation is something you have to go through the courts
about, right? So that's I think a very important way of thinking
that this idea is basically when you have a concrete object of
yours that's being taken by somebody else or in somebody else's possession
and you're protecting it, that's a way of understanding how עביד איניש
דינא לנפשיה avid inish dina l'nafsheih works. It would not work if
you're just trying to get compensated. Of course, the flip side of
all of this is that this undermines the, creates anarchy, it undermines
the courts and their authority and so on and creates anarchy. And
what is exactly the balance there? And that's the other side. I
should say that the other approach of this, rather than seeing it
as this idea of self-protection, is what the רמב"ם Rambam says. רמב"ם
Rambam says, he has this in הלכות סנהדרין. Hilchos Sanhedrin. And the
רמב"ם Rambam says, a בית דין beis din is made up of
three, but really מעיקר הדין me'ikar hadin you can have a בית
דין beis din of one. And then he says and that's why
עביד איניש דינא לנפשיה avid inish dina l'nafsheih because you can basically
be a בית דין beis din of one. Okay, now what exactly
happened to the idea that you're a little bit of a קרוב
אצל עצמו, karov eitzel atzmo, I don't know, but somehow the רמב"ם
Rambam actually understands that it really is דינא. dina. It's really not
like, as opposed to us, we're looking at it like in a
בבא קמא Bava Kamma sense, like you're about to damage me, what
can I do to protect myself from being damaged, or even if
the object's already in your property, what can I do to protect
my property? Right? The רמב"ם Rambam is looking at it in a
סנהדרין Sanhedrin sense. Here I am, I'm a דיין, dayan, I know
all the facts and I'm going to go ahead and do my
own... so according to the רמב"ם Rambam maybe it could even be
to get compensated, maybe it's not just to protect concrete property. Very
strange idea, but that's the way the רמב"ם Rambam frames it. Let's
continue in the גמרא. Gemara. I know,
he doesn't explain it. Yeah, okay. So the גמרא Gemara says like
this, "Okay, תא שמע, ta shma, come and hear. הממלא
חצר חבירו כדי יין וכדי שמן,
hamemalei chatzar
chaveiro kadei yayin v'kadei shemen, if you fill up your friend's yard,
there you go Jonathan, with these barrels of wine and of oil.
בעל החצר משבר ויוצא משבר ונכנס. ba'al hachatzar meshabeir v'yotzei meshabeir v'nichnas.
So the owner of the yard who needs to get into his
house can break them going in and break them going out indiscriminately."
Okay, so that seems to be, so why is it a case
of הפסד? hefsed? Just go to court and get the court to
remove it. So you could say, "What do you mean? I want
to go to sleep, I want to use my house, isn't that
a הפסד?" hefsed? But anyway, אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק משבר ויוצא
לביתו ומשבר ונכנס להביא זכויותיו. amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak meshabeir v'yotzei
l'veito u'meshabeir v'nichnas l'havi zechuyosav. Yes, actually it means he's going in
and out and he breaks them because in order to bring the
case to court he's got to go out and get out of
his house or he's got to go into his house to get
whatever evidence he has that it's his yard. All right, I mean
you could have said, I think you could have said it's just
a case of הפסד, hefsed, that if I'm not able to use
my house it's a הפסד hefsed case. תא שמע, ta shma, מנין
לנרצע שכלו ימיו, minayin lenirtza shekalu yamav, how do you know that
an עבד עברי eved Ivri who's been working for you until the
יובל, Yovel, right, you pierced his ear, so he's been with you
a very long time, and now ורבו מסרב בו לצאת, v'rabbo mesareiv
bo latzeit, and the owner is sort of urging him to go,
right? And he doesn't want to go, maybe he's now gotten old,
a slave who doesn't want to leave after this amount of time.
וחבל ועשה בו חבורה, v'chabel v'asah bo chavurah, and in order to
get him to leave the master hits him and makes a wound,
how do you know שפטור, shepatur, that the master is exempt? תלמוד
לומר לא תקחו כופר לשוב, talmud lomar lo tikchu kofer lashuv, it
says לא תקחו כופר לנפש רוצח לשוב אל עיר מקלטו. lo tikchu
kofer lenefesh rotzeach lashuv el ir miklato. So we're reading it לשב,
lashav, thank you, לנוסי, lanusi, יאמר קלו לשוב לשבת, yamer kalu lashuv
lashavet, thank you.
Okay, so do not take an atonement payment לשב, lashav, לא תקחו
כופר לשב. lo tikchu kofer lashav.
Don't take a כופר kofer for somebody who should be, that's he's
either שבת sheshas who he's staying here when he should be leaving,
or somebody who should be returning to his ancestral home and is
refusing to return. Anyway we're learning from a פסוק. pasuk. But anyway
you see that it's a type of עביד איניש דינא לנפשיה avid
inish dina l'nafsheih that you are trying to, you know, get him
out of your house, protect, I mean you know...
that's a הפסד, hefsed, right, because he's like eating from my food?
Right, exactly, exactly. That's what the גמרא Gemara is going to say.
הכא במאי עסקינן בעבדא גנבא. hacha b'mai askinan b'avda ganva. No, because
you could just stop feeding him, but you know, by presumably, so
okay, but he's still going to be, I don't know, living in
the slave quarters, maybe I want to put somebody else up there.
Anyway, the גמרא Gemara one easily imagines that the גמרא Gemara could
have said that there was other types of פסידא *pseida*, but the
פסידא *pseida* the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* focuses on is you're afraid he's
going to steal from you. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
where was it? הכא במאי עסקינן בעבד גנבא *Hacha bemai askinan be'eved
ganva*. ארי דעדנא לא גנב והשתא גנב *Arei de'idna lo ganav vehashta
ganav*? I don't understand. How did you tolerate him until now? So
until now presumably he wasn't stealing. No. ארי דעדנא הוה אימתא דמריה
עליה *Arei de'idna hava aimta demarei aleia*. Until now you were his
master and therefore he was afraid. השתא לית ליה אימתא דמריה עליה
*Hashta leit lei aimta demarei aleia*. Now he doesn't have the fear
of the master. So anyway, בקיצור *bekitzur*, keeping him around you're afraid
it actually is going to be a case of some type of
a loss. Okay, רב Rav פפא בר יצחק אמר *Rav Pappa bar
Yitzchak amar* בעבד שמסר לו רבו שפחה כנענית *be'eved shemasar lo rabbo
shifcha Kena'anit* that he was married to a non-Jewish
maidservant, which you're allowed an עבד עברי *eved Ivri* is allowed to
do. ארי דעדנא היתירא *Arei de'idna heteira*, until now it was permissible
because he had a status of an עבד עברי *eved Ivri*, והשתא
איסורא *vehashta issura*, now it's forbidden, and therefore you are using violence
not to protect your property, but this really is a סנהדרין *Sanhedrin*
discussion about the use of violence to protect to stop somebody from
doing an עבירה *aveira*. Okay, which is a separate discussion, which we
won't get into. All right, so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
like this. תא שמע ta shma: *Ta shema*. And this is why
we're bringing it in here. המניח את הכד *Hamaniach et hakad* ברשות
הרבים *berishut harabbim* ובא אחר ונתקל בה *uva acher venitkal bah* ושיברה
פטור patur
*veshibrah patur*. So you leave it in ברשות הרבים *berishut harabbim* and
somebody comes and trips on it and breaks it, he's exempt. Okay,
and that we've discussed. Is it because אדם *adam* is not really
מועד לעולם *mu'ad le'olam* or because you were negligent? But anyway, טעמא
דנתקל בה *Ta'ama denitkal bah*. The reason he's exempt is because he
accidentally tripped on it. הא שיברה חייב chayav. *Ha shibrah chayav*. If
he intentionally broke it he'd be חייב chayav, *chayav*. And we're now
implicitly importing Rav's position earlier that is you fill the whole ברשות
הרבים *berishut harabbim* with these pitchers. Okay, remember this was the question
we asked yesterday. So if you fill the whole ברשות הרבים *berishut
harabbim* with the pitchers, then he should be allowed to break it
intentionally because he wants access to the ברשות הרבים *berishut harabbim*. He
needs to get through the ברשות הרבים *berishut harabbim*. So the fact
that he is still going to be liable shows that shows that
לא עביד איניש דינא לנפשיה avid inish dina l'nafshei, *lo avid inish
dina lenafsheih*. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this. Where
were we? הא שיברה חייב chayav *Ha shibrah chayav*. אמר רב Rav
זביד משמיה דרבא *Amar Rav Zevid mishmeih deRava*, הוא הדין אפילו שיברה
*Hu hadin afilu shibrah*, no, even if you broke it you're okay.
והאי דקתני נתקל *Vehai dekatani nitkal*, איידי דבעי למיתנא סיפא *aidi deba'ei
limitna seifa* אם הוזק בעל הבית חייב chayav בנתקל *im huzak ba'al
habayit chayav benitkal*. Since the end is going to say that if
you if you got damaged by the pot, the owner of the
pot has to pay you. So that in that case דוקא נתקל
*davka nitkal*. That's only if you accidentally tripped on it. הא שיברה
*Ha shibrah*, if you got damaged because you intentionally broke it, לא
*lo*, then he doesn't have to pay you, דהוא אזיק אנפשיה *dehu
azik anafsheih*, you brought it upon yourself. תני רישא נתקל *Tani reisha
nitkal*. So therefore it says נתקל *nitkal*. But the reality is if
the ברשות הרבים *berishut harabbim* is filled with pots and I have
to get through, I am allowed to intentionally go ahead and break
the pots in order to get through.
Okay, so okay, so that now again the interesting question is, right,
is that considered to be מקום פסידא *mekom pseida* or not מקום
פסידא *mekom pseida*? Right, it sounds like the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* considers
it to be not מקום פסידא *mekom pseida* because it's asking it
only on the one position that says, right, everybody agrees מקום פסידא
*mekom pseida* would be allowed, right? So the fact that the but
anyway, so it's interesting, why is that not מקום פסידא *mekom pseida*?
Like you're preventing my use of ברשות הרבים *berishut harabbim*. Right, so
it's interesting whether the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* was considering that to be
not מקום פסידא *mekom pseida* or not, but either way the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says you really are allowed to go ahead and break
it. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* continues. Okay, תא שמע Ta
shma. וקצתה את כפה ממון *Ta shema vekatzota et kappah mamon*. So
this is where we learn out the idea of בושת *boshet*, the
woman who's intervening when her husband is fighting another man and she
grabs the other man by his privates. It says cut off her
hand, which we say doesn't literally mean that, it means you pay
the cost of בושת *boshet*. So here's the interesting question which you
all asked, I think it's this is the obvious question you ask
when you read the פסוקים Psukim *pesukim*. What did she do that
was wrong? She was trying to protect her husband. And that was
עביד איניש דינא לנפשיה avid inish dina l'nafshei *avid inish dina lenafsheih*.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says מאי לאו *Mai lav* בשאינה
יכולה להציל על ידי דבר אחר *beshe'eina yechola lehatzil al yedei davar
acher*? Presumably it means this was the only thing she could do
to stop the other guy from beating up her husband. And therefore
it is a case of עביד איניש דינא לנפשיה avid inish dina
l'nafshei. *avid inish dina lenafsheih*. Why should she have to pay? Now
by the way presumably here's an interesting question. Before we were asking
is does עביד איניש דינא לנפשיה avid inish dina l'nafshei, *avid inish
dina lenafsheih* allow you so much to injure another person, personal injury,
and it seemed like yes. Here's another question. Let's say I can
recoup, you're going to beat me up and I can recoup all
those things, צער, נזק, שבת, ריפוי, בושת *tza'ar, nezek, shevet, ripui, boshet*,
etc. Would you call that איכא פסידא ika p'seida. *ika pseida* or
ליכא פסידא leka p'seida *leika pseida*? I would still call it איכא
פסידא ika p'seida. *ika pseida*. Excuse me, me being beaten up, it's
not a piece of property that is in the end I'm going
to get my money back, right? Even if you pay me, right,
I mean certainly if it's a permanent injury, then you could say
you're never really recovering it. But regardless, any type of personal injury
you would think is a case of איכא פסידא *ika pseida*, right?
I would think so. Anyway, it's interesting again that the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* is asking this presumably assuming that it's a case of ליכא
פסידא leka p'seida. *leika pseida*, which I don't really understand. Okay, but
anyway the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says maybe because it's all it is,
it's not actual injury, it's just embarrassment. But nevertheless, most people I
think would rather not be embarrassed than be embarrassed and get compensated
for it. I guess it depends how big the compensation is. Anyway,
so the גמרא Gemara presumably thinking that this is a case of
ליכא פסידא leka p'seida. says, "Look, how come you have to, how
come you weren't allowed to do it?" Presumably it's a case you
had no loss. And nevertheless, עביד איניש דינא לנפשיה, avid inish dina
lenafshay, presumably because it's a case of ליכא פסידא. leka p'seida Okay,
actually forget it. The guy she's grabbing the private is embarrassed, but
she's trying to protect her husband from actual personal injury, so to
me that would really seem to be a case of, of איכא
פסידא. Anyway, so it's not clear why the גמרא Gemara is only
asking it according to the position of ליכא פסידא. But anyway, the
גמרא Gemara says: so why is it? It must be a case
that she couldn't do anything else, and it should be עביד איניש
דינא לנפשיה Avid Inish Dina L'nafshei. so she shouldn't have to pay.
So the גמרא Gemara says, מאי לאו בשאינו יכול להציל על ידי
דבר אחר mai lav b'she'eino yachol l'hatzil al yedei davar acher she
had no alternative? לא בשיהכול להציל על ידי דבר אחר. lo b'sheyachol
l'hatzil al yedei davar acher. No, she could have done it in
some other way and therefore this is sort of like pulling the
cow out from under, like, but this is actually not focusing on
one object versus the other, it's you could have done it in
a- if you overstep the bounds of what was necessary, you're no
longer doing דין. din. Now you're going excessive and therefore you are
not allowed to do that and you have to pay. So the
גמרא Gemara says, אבל אינו יכול להציל על ידי דבר אחר פטורה?
aval eino yachol l'hatzil al yedei davar acher p'tura? Are you telling
me that if she had no alternative she's- she would be פטורה,
p'tura, exempt by- by seizing this guy's private? אי הכי דתני סיפא,
i hachi detani seifa, the end of that ברייתא braisa teaches, ושלחה
ידה. v'shilcha yada. The פסוק pasuk says she sent forth her hand,
פרט לשליח בית דין, p'rat lishliach beis din, that excludes the case
when she gets a שליח בית דין shliach beis din to- somebody
from the court intervenes, then he's going to be exempt. The court
officer would be exempt. So the גמרא Gemara says if that's true,
why does it only exempt the court officer? לכתוב ולתני בדידה. liftiv
v'lisni b'dideha. Why not just say that there are cases even with
her that she's exempt? במה דברים אמורים, b'meh devarim amurim, when does
she have to pay? בשיהכול להציל על ידי דבר אחר. b'sheyachol l'hatzil
al yedei davar acher. She could have saved her husband through some
less drastic means. אבל אינו יכול להציל על ידי דבר אחר, aval
eino yachol l'hatzil al yedei davar acher, if she couldn't have saved
her husband through less drastic means, פטורה, p'tura, she'd be exempt because
of עביד איניש דינא לנפשיה. Avid Inish Dina L'nafshei? Why not say
that? גמרא Gemara says הכי נמי קאמר. hachi nami ka'amar. You know
what? It is saying that. במה דברים אמורים בשיהכול להציל על ידי
דבר אחר. b'meh devarim amurim b'sheyachol l'hatzil al yedei davar acher. When
is she liable? If she could have saved her husband through less
drastic means. אבל אינו יכול להציל על ידי דבר אחר, aval eino
yachol l'hatzil al yedei davar acher, if she couldn't have done that,
then נעשה ידה כשליח בית דין ופטורה, na'asa yada k'shliach beis din
u'ptura, then she's acting like an officer of the court and she's
exempt. So when it says an officer of the court is exempt,
it really means that when you are עביד איניש דינא לנפשיה, Avid
Inish Dina L'nafshei when you're acting properly to protect yourself, you become
like an officer of the court. So this last line by the
way, you know, although the גמרא Gemara just does it to get
away from the evidence of the ברייתא, braisa, supports a רמב"ם Rambam
idea, actually sees you as, oh, not you're okay because you're protecting
your property, what you're doing is seen as acting on behalf of
the court. Okay, so that's actually a very interesting framing. By the
way, I'm waiting for somebody to ask me, why is this- why
is this דינא לנפשיה? dina l'nafsha? She's protecting her husband, she's not
protecting herself. Okay now, could you say, you know, אשתו כגופו, ishto
k'gufo, בעלה כגופו, ba'alah k'gufo, you know, protecting your family, protecting your
kids, all those are things that it is protecting yourself. So let
me ask you a question. Let's say it's a real third party.
Let's say I know here, you know, that Charlie has been holding
on to, you know, הלל's Hillel wallet and denying that he has
it, and I go ahead and I see the- I see it
on Charlie's
property and הלל Hillel can't come and get it, but I finally
have an opportunity to get it. Can I knock out Charlie's teeth
and retrieve- and retrieve it? Right, so if you think it's like
the רמב"ם, Rambam, that you're actually a בית דין beis din of
one, then maybe you could even do it for somebody else, although
then you start getting real anarchy, right? But anyway, but if it's
just a right to protect my own property, I can't. So that's
why I think the לנפשיה l'nafshei is very critical question here.
Yes, it is לנפשיה l'nafshei in this case because, I mean, in
antiquity she would depend on her husband.
Right, it directly impacts her. Right, I agree. And I think that,
you know, that this is- I- but I did want to raise
the question. I do think it's pretty clear that the גמרא's Gemara
all these questions are for yourself and not for a third party,
right? Yes.
So she is שליח בית דין shliach beis din and רמב"ם Rambam
says she is in fact acting as בית דין beis din one.
So therefore, woman can be a בית דין beis din for דיני
ממונות. dinei mamonot.
She could be a שליח בית דין. shliach beis din. Alright, anyway.
Even if she's a שליח shliach if you-
oh, that's an interesting point. If the רמב"ם Rambam says that she's
דן יחידי, dan yachidi, I haven't thought about that. That's a good
point. Because this is a שליח בית דין shliach beis din a
woman could be, but the רמב"ם Rambam actually has you being a
דן יחידי, dan yachidi, the דיין, dayan, so precisely... Definitely very- that's
a good point. You have a woman here as the דיין. dayan.
Okay, there you go. Alright, anyway.
Her יד. yad.
Her יד. yad. Okay. Anyway, but again I also repeat the idea
about whether the גמרא Gemara is considering personal injury. If you're going
to suffer personal injury and be able to recover, get compensation, to
me that would always be considered איכא פסידא. But it sounds like
the גמרא Gemara was considering it to be a ליכא פסידא case.
Okay, תא שמע: הרי שהיתה דרך הרבים ועוברת בתוך שדהו. harei she'aysa
derech harabbim u'overet b'toch sadeihu. You had a public thoroughfare going through
your field. נטלה, Natla,
now you did not want it going cutting through your field. It
was, you know, obviously costing you, it was costing you
a loss in terms of plowing and whatever. So what you did
is you seized it, ונתן להם מן הצד, unasan lahem min hatzad,
and you gave them some other path at the edge of your
field, which was more, which is better for you. מה שנתן נתן,
Ma shenasan nasan, what you gave you gave, ושלו לא הגיעו, veshelo
lo higi'o,
but you do not get to keep your own,
because you're basically, they still have rights to the first one. ואי
אמרת עביד איניש דינא לנפשיה, Ve'i amart avid inish dina lenafshay, but
if you can be עביד איניש דינא לנפשיה, meaning now we're assuming
that the swap was a legitimate swap and the reason, so they
really do get the one that you gave them, but the reason
ושלו לא הגיעו veshelo lo higi'o is because they're going to keep
on using the main one and you can't stop them. But why
can't you stop them? Okay? ואי אמרת עביד איניש דינא לנפשיה, Ve'i
amart avid inish dina lenafshay, לינקוט פזרא וליתב, lincot pazra velesav,
go ahead and take like a shovel or whatever a פזרא pazra
is and sit there at the, at the, in front of the
road and hit anybody who tries to use it. Okay? What's the
problem? So אמר זביד משמיה דרבא, Amar Zevid mishmei deRava, גזירה שמא
יתן להם דרך עקלתון. gezeira shema yitein lahem derech akalason. You're right.
Really you should be allowed to because you gave, you did a
fair swap, and,
but we're not going to let you, or you know, take the
one that, that was going through the middle of your road because
we're afraid that sometimes it won't be a fair swap. Sometimes the
one you'll give them will be a roundabout path and not a
straightforward path. So therefore we're not, it's, we're going to consider it
to not be a fair swap even if it was, and we
want, and they still have rights to the first one. רב אשי
אמר, Rav Ashi amar, כגון שנתן להם דרך עקלתון. kegon shenasan lahem
derech akalason.
No, I'm not going to make a גזירה, gezeira, but the case
in the ברייתא Braisa that's talking about is a case when you
did, when it was not a fair swap. And since it wasn't
a fair swap, of course, the question is if it wasn't a
fair swap, why did they get the one from the side? Let
it go back to the original state. We'll get to that in
a minute. But if it wasn't a fair swap, you did not
have a right to take their more central path. Okay? רב אשי
אמר, Rav Ashi amar, רב אשי Rav Ashi says, כל מן הצד
דרך עקלתון הוא. kol min hatzad derech akalason hu.
Anytime it is a different path from the one that you started
with, it is an out-of-the-way path. Why? קרוב לזה ורחוק לזה. Karov
lezeh verachok lezeh.
Some people benefit and some people lose out. Right? Because you know,
anytime you move it, it's going to be more convenient for some
people and less convenient for others. So there's always going to be
a way in which this is less, less ideal for some people,
this new path that you've given. And therefore it is never considered
to be an equivalent swap. All right? So the גמרא Gemara says,
אי הכי, ei hachi, if it wasn't an equivalent swap and therefore
it didn't count and therefore they have the first road, אמאי ושלו
לא הגיעו? amai veshelo lo higi'o? Why do you not, or תוספות
Tosafos has the גירסא, girsa, אמאי מה שנתן נתן? amai ma shenasan
nasan? Why do they, why do they
get the rights to the, to the new thing you gave them?
If the whole swap wasn't fair, then at least you should be
able to still have what you gave them, to keep what you
gave them. So the גמרא Gemara says, לימא להו, leima lehu, tell
them, שקולו דידכו והבו לי דידי. shkulu didchu vehavu li didi. Fine.
Keep the one that's yours, give me back the thing that was
always mine. No, משום דרב יהודה. mishum deRav Yehuda. That's because of
רב יהודה. Rav Yehuda. דאמר רב יהודה, De'amar Rav Yehuda, מצר שהחזיקו
בו רבים, meitzar shehecheziku bo rabbim,
if you have a path that was seized by the masses, אסור
לקלקלו, assur lekalkelo,
then they sort of get it by like right of eminent domain
or something. So therefore you're really stuck. Meaning, the swap didn't count,
legally didn't count, so they never lost rights to the first one,
but once they started using the, the one on the side, then
they've basically acquired that as well. So you're out on both ways.
Okay? But bottom line is that you, in principle though, if they
were using a path they didn't have rights to, you'd be able
to stand at the, you know, at it and like and you
know beat off anybody that tries to use it. Yes, Charlie?
So it sounds from that interpretation that the equivalent of eminent domain
in הלכה Halacha just does not automatically guarantee you compensation.
Correct. Yeah, that would, right, exactly. There would not be compensation. Okay.
So now the גמרא Gemara says like this, one last one, תא
שמע. בעל הבית שהניח פאה
מצד אחד. Ba'al habayis sheheniach peah mitzad echad. So you left פאה
peah at one side of your field. ובאו עניים ונטלו מצד אחר.
Uva'u aniyim venatlu mitzad acher. And they took from the other side
of the field. זה וזה פאה. Zeh vaze peah. They're both פאה.
peah. Okay?
So we, so why is that? Why don't you, why aren't you
allowed to sort of use force? ואי אמרת עביד איניש דינא לנפשיה,
Ve'i amart avid inish dina lenafshay, אמאי זה וזה פאה? amai zeh
vaze peah? Same question. לינקוט פזרא וליתב. Lincot pazra velesav. Go ahead
and, you know, take a, a shovel and sit and prevent them
from, from getting, like presumably it sounds like, you know, they get,
they took what they took, but now they're also allowed to take
what you sort of gave them. Okay? When you thought they were
going to take from your side, from the first side of the
field. So why is that? Why don't you just beat them off
and say, hey guys, you already took פאה peah from the other
side. I'm not letting you take from, from this stuff. So the
גמרא Gemara says, אמר רבא, Amar Rava, מאי זה וזה פאה לפטור
מן המעשר? Mai zeh vaze peah liftur min hama'aser? No, it doesn't
mean that you really have to give them the stuff that, you
know, they already took from side A, you don't have to give
them the stuff that you had left aside from side B. You
are allowed to protect that and to prevent them from taking it.
So what does it mean that it's פאה? Peah? It means that
it was momentarily פאה. Peah. Like you, you left aside side B.
Then they seized on side A. So basically as soon as they
started taking פאה Peah on side A, you reclaimed your stuff on
side B. So what does it mean that it was פאה? Peah?
Not you have to give it to them. It means it had
momentarily been פאה. Peah. And the relevance of it momentarily having been
פאה Peah is that now you don't have to give מעשר Maaser
from it now that you have retaken it and it's yours. דתניא
De'tanya which we taught in a ברייתא, Braita, המפקיר כרמו והשכים בבוקר
ובצרו, Hamaphkir Karmo V'hishkim BaBoker U'vatzro,
if you were מפקיר Maphkir your vineyard and then in the next
morning you got up early and you reclaimed it before anybody else
could take it—this is the way you could get out of giving
certain of the of the agricultural gifts because basically it was it
was הפקר Hefker for overnight and then you reclaimed it in the
morning, then חייב בפרט ובעוללות ובשכחה ובפאה, Chayav B'peret U'v'olelot U'v'shichcha U'v'peah,
you still have to give all of the gifts to the poor,
but ופטור
מן המעשר U'pattur Min HaMaaser you're exempt from מעשר. Maaser. So I'm
not going to get into the פסוקים we learn it from, but
anyway that's the point here. They took פאה Peah on another side
of the field, that somehow counts as פאה Peah even though you
didn't intentionally leave it, which is an interesting point. You're entitled to
re-seize what you left, but because what you left had momentarily been
פאה, Peah, you now are exempt from מעשר. Maaser. But it really
has nothing to do with that your inability that you're not allowed
to protect it. So how do we פסקן Pasken about all of
this?
Overwhelmingly the ראשונים Rishonim פסקן Pasken עביד איניש דינא לנפשיה אפילו במקום
דליכא פסידא. Avid Inish Dina L'nafshei Aphilu B'makom De'leika Psida.
Okay, which is sort of where all of the evidence in the
גמרא was going, that you are עביד איניש דינא לנפשיה. As I
said, there is interesting questions about about what the what the
logic is behind it. Is it about protecting my property from loss,
or is it about my ability to act as a דיין? Dayan?
The
is the מרדכי's Mordechai point that all these cases in the גמרא
are cases where there was a concrete object that you were protecting,
right, is makes a lot of sense in terms of that first
approach and stops this thing from getting out of hand and becoming
total anarchy where everybody can just steal other people's property and saying
they're being compensated for some loss or for some injury. But that
is an interesting question like what are the limits of it. Somebody
asked the רשב"א Rashba once a שאלה She'eila and he said, I
have to I have a case in court and I know that
I am obviously right. I know that this guy stole my stuff,
but I don't have my documentation. Am I allowed to forge documentation
in order to win the case in court? Okay, which I mean,
you wouldn't be asking the שאלה She'eila if you really was just
סתם Stam a thief and a forger. I know I'm right, I
just lost the documentation. Can I forge the documentation? Do we say
עביד איניש דינא לנפשיה? So the רשב"א, Rashba, any guesses what the
רשב"א Rashba answer? What he said,
he said you've got to be crazy! That completely undermines, you know,
the authority of the court. It turns the whole sense of דין
Din and justice and אמת Emet into a mockery. Right, so the
whole question here is even if we conceptualize this as protecting your
property, at what stage are you undermining the authority of the court?
Right, and again some of these cases like when as you were
pointing out, when the damage was imminent and I'm preventing damage from
occurring are much more obvious that you should have a license to
protect yourself from suffering damage than it is when
actually the damage has occurred and your object is in somebody else's
house. And again the also very interesting thing is that you're allowed
to do it even to the extent of causing injury, physical injury
on somebody else's person. Question is how far would that go? But
balanced by the idea that the גמרא says if you have ways
of doing it with less force, you can't use excessive force or
cause excessive damage. So it's all within certain parameters. Yes.
And how do we balance this with המוציא מחבירו עליו הראיה? HaMotzi
MeChaveiro Alav HaRe'ayah? I mean, especially if it's after the fact. I
mean, I can understand setting up a an analysis that was framing
it this way as acting to prevent damage. Right. To the fact,
how do I know that you're not taking something that's not really
yours?
What do you mean? What's the scenario?
I don't know. You I have something of mine. I go into
your חצר Chatzer to get back. Right. But isn't that also המוציא
מחבירו עליו הראיה? HaMotzi MeChaveiro Alav HaRe'ayah? What, don't I have to
go to בית דין Beit Din and I have to show that
that's really mine and taking it from your property is against—Right.
So oh, I see your point. So the question if, meaning obviously
you go ahead and you break my teeth in order to retrieve
something, right, I can now take you to court and sue you
for personal injury. And you would have to prove that you would
have to bring evidence that that object was yours. But once you
brought evidence that that object was yours, you wouldn't have to pay
me for breaking my teeth. Meaning you're right, the act of that's
an important point. The act of seizing it doesn't prove that it
was your property. עביד איניש דינא לנפשיה means that you're allowed to
act to cause injury to the person or injury to the person's
property if you need to in order to retrieve it, but you're
in but you in the end could be sued and will have
to prove that you were acting properly. Right. So that's that is
a really important point. Yes, thank you for raising that. But then—
But then it becomes me, the injured party, who has to sue
you, and you are now whole already, so the טירחא tircha is
now essentially on me, right, you know. But anyway, but yes, you
will have to, you, yes, this doesn't remove the necessity of proving
that you're right if you do get brought to court, but what
it does do is it gives you license to do what you
need to do in order to get the object back. Okay. So
משנה. Mishnah. נשבר כדו ברשות
הרבים,
Nishbar kado
b'reshut harabim, the pitcher broke in רשות הרבים, reshut harabim, והוחלק אחד
במים, ve'huchlak echad b'mayim, somebody slipped on the water. So essentially you
made a בור bor in רשות הרבים reshut harabim because your pitcher
broke and it spilled in רשות הרבים. reshut harabim. או שלקה בחרסית,
O shelaka b'charisit, or somebody got injured on the shard of the
pitcher, okay, חייב. chayav, You're חייב, chayav you made a בור bor
in רשות הרבים. reshut harabim. So one question is going to be
what negligence did you have in making the בור, bor, in making
this בור? bor? Right, what was the, you know, how did your
pitcher break? Were you negligent or not? Are you חייב chayav even
if your בור bor was made באונס? b'ones? Okay, that's one question.
But it's clear the type of a בור, bor, seems to be.
רבי יהודה אומר במתכוין חייב ואינו מתכוין פטור. Rabbi Yehuda omer bim'khaven
chayav ve'eino m'khaven patur. He seems to say you're not חייב chayav
in all cases. Intentionally, what's intentionally? You really tried to break it?
Anyway, intentionally you're חייב, chayav unintentionally you're exempt. Does that mean the
degree of negligence? Anyway, we will see. Okay, so it seems to
be בור. bor. Let's see what the גמרא says. אמר רב יהודה
אמר רב, Amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav, לא שנו אלא שטינפו כליו
במים. lo shanu ela she'tinfu kelav b'mayim. What we are talking about
is you slipped in the water and your nice silk dress got
stained in the water. אבל הוא עצמו פטור, Aval hu atzmo patur,
but if you slipped in the water and banged your head on
the ground, then if it's injury that happened to you yourself, you're
exempt. Why is that? קרקע עולם הזיקתו, Karka olam hizzikato, because you
were only injured by the ground. You weren't injured by my בור.
bor. Now, okay, so there's going to be two important issues that
are going to be going on here. All right. One question is,
did were you
מפקיר mafkir the water or not? רב Rav is of the opinion,
you might remember this going back to the first פרק, perek, that
if you have a physical object of yours in the רשות הרבים
reshut harabim that somebody trips over, that you own the object, he
considers that to be a שור, shor, not a בור. bor. Some
people might remember that. Okay. Whereas שמואל Shmuel says no, whether you
own it or you don't own it, it's a בור. bor. Now
the reason that that is relevant is for the following issue. One
case is what is that a בור bor is פטור patur if
it causes damage to vessels. It's only חייב chayav, if it causes
injury to a person
or death of an animal. But it's פטור pattur if it causes
damage to vessels, that's a בור. bor. So if it's a שור,
shor, this object, because you still own it, you're חייב chayav if
it causes damage to vessels. So רב Rav says the guy's shirt
got damaged. Okay. So the only way he could be חייב chayav
for the shirt being damaged is if he conceptualizes it as a
שור. shor. If it's a בור, bor, it's exempt for causing damage
to person's objects. You guys with me here? Yes? Okay. So number
one is if we're talking about the vessels being damaged, he has
to conceptualize it as a שור. shor. That's one question. But here's
another question. The other question is, when I am חייב chayav for
digging my בור, bor, okay,
normally what would you imagine happens? Here's this guy, he's walking, la
la la, he trips and falls, right, okay, there you go, yes
sir, he bangs himself on the ground. That's קרקע עולם, karka olam,
right? He's banging himself on the floor of the ground. So you
would assume that the obligation for בור bor is causing a stumbling
block, a hazard, even though the person the injury occurs by, you
know, by just the simple ground, okay. So therefore it should be
the same if
I put a thing there and he walks on it and he
trips and his face hits the ground, it's also קרקע עולם, karka
olam, but basically a בור bor is causing a stumbling block and
then he hits himself on the ground. Now that is not necessarily
how בור bor is understood.
First of all, even in the case of the קרקע עולם karka
olam here, it was a certain type of a קרקע עולם karka
olam that you created. Like you sort of created that type of
a ground with that depth that caused it etc. as opposed to
here, the ground was always here, you just put a stumbling block.
Okay. Also, the גמרא is going to have an opinion that the
חיוב chiyuv here by a בור bor is not for hitting the
ground, but it's a very weird idea, it's the הבל, hevel, it's
like the heavy air in the בור bor is why you're חייב,
chayav but not the actual hitting of the ground. So that's all
very complicated and we're going to see that later. But what you
have to know for now is that since here you didn't even
dig the ground in which he's hitting, he's hitting ground that was
always there, you just put the stumbling block, you just put the
water, so רב Rav is saying you're not חייב chayav, if he
hits the ground. Your thing, he has to be damaged on your
thing itself. So if he slips... And the water I don't know
gets into his face and causes him to choke or something you'd
be חייב chayav because the water is doing the damage. But it's
very unlikely that the water does damage to the person. So therefore
since רב Rav is saying you're only חייב chayav. if the water
itself the thing itself damages the person, the most reasonable thing is
that it's not that he was damaged but that his shirt was
damaged, right? His vessels were damaged. But then that has to be
a type of a שור. shor. So רב Rav says this is
a שור shor if the guy trips and falls then it's sort
of like now you might think that I'd be חייב chayav. in
this case. Here's an ox, like my ox, those are the horns.
It pushes this guy over and then he falls and he doesn't
get gored by it but he falls because of the impact of
hitting the ground. The ox pushes him and he hits the floor.
I would think that you should be חייב, chayav. right? But רב
Rav, is saying no, if the שור shor directly did not injure
the guy, he got hit by the ground, then he's exempt. So
this thing is a שור shor because you own it, you trip
over it, you hit the ground, you're exempt, the guy's exempt. He's
only חייב chayav by direct damage that the שור shor does. So
that would be that the water stained the clothes. That's the way
רב Rav reads the case. Yes.
Is there any thought about צרורות tzrorot or like indirect damage from
an אב? av?
Yeah, so I mean it's an interesting, well first of all, you
mean why isn't that like a type of a צרורות tzrorot of
קרן? keren? I mean it's a little different. It's like a direct
contact and then the injury happened later, but yeah, I hear that.
Yes.
Is it קרנא? Kerena? What?
Is it קרנא? Kerena?
Oh, so that's an interesting question of what type of a שור
shor is this. Is it רגל regel but then you'd be פטור
pattur in רשות הרבים? reshut harabbim? So תוספות Tosafot sort of says
it's some type of a generic שור, shor, some common denominator of
רגל regel and קרן. keren. That's also... that's a question we had
a while back. Okay, yes.
It seems like all these categories are like avoiding the issue of
like how did the guy get there?
What do you mean?
In other words, he got there because somebody was negligent. I mean,
the ground doesn't do something to anybody.
Right, right, right, I understand. That... so
the whole idea of the, you know, first of... of all these
פרקים prakim about ארבעה אבות נזיקין arba'ah avot nezikin is that it's
not just a question of who was negligent. It has to be
negligence operating within these formal categories. And that can be frustrating, I
understand. But you know, law in general, but if you just have
a general question of negligence, it's also a very abstract and hard
to pinpoint. So here it operates within identifying these sort of concrete
categories. You know, so even if yes, you were... the guy was
negligent, that's not enough to say that he's חייב. chayav You know,
even though the guy who put it here was to blame, that's
not enough of a basis for חיוב chiyyuv to be חייב.
chayav It's almost focusing... it seems like in this specific case, the
property is more important than the person.
Well, not more important, it's just the circumstances. Not more important, the
circumstances. If this wasn't water, if this was a knife and the
person tripped on it and the knife actually directly injured, then you'd
be חייב. chayav It's just the circumstances are such that the person
isn't injured by the water, okay, he's injured by the ground. Okay,
so the גמרא says like this. So that's what he says. כי
אמריתה קמיה דשמואל, Ki amriteh kumei diShmuel, when I said it to
שמואל, Shmuel, אמר לי מכדי, amar li michdi, אבנא וסכינא ומשא מבור
למדנו. avna vesakina umassa mibor lamadnu. No,
those are a בור. bor. So the water is a בור, bor,
whether you own it or don't own it. דכולן אני קרי בהן
שור ולא אדם חמור ולא כלים. Dekulan ani karei behun shor velo
adam chamor velo kelim. By a בור bor it says that an
ox or a person gets damaged... an ox means... I mean an
ox and a donkey get damaged, an ox and not a person,
meaning a person who dies, and a vessel, you're not חייב chayav
in a בור. bor. So if the water is a בור, bor,
we're not talking that your clothes got damaged. Your clothes, you'd be
פטור pattur. on.
והני מילי לענין קטלא. Vahani milei le'inyan ketala. The fact that you're
exempt in a בור bor for a person is if a person
dies. אבל לענין נזיקין, Aval le'inyan nezikin, if a person is injured,
אדם חייב וכלים פטורים. adam chayav vekelim patturim. Then for injury, a
person you're חייב chayav for injury to a person, but you're exempt
from injury to vessels. Because the גמרא says by vessels it says...
it says, you know, שבירתן זו היא מיתתן. sheviratan zo hi mitatan.
When a vessel is injured it's dead, like you know, it doesn't
have these different degrees, it's like it's not usable anymore.
Okay, so you're exempt for killing people, but you're חייב chayav for
injuring them, and you're exempt for all damage to vessels. So this
water is a בור. bor. And therefore, obviously we're not talking about
that your shirt was damaged, you'd be פטור. pattur So רב, Rav
now רב Rav would say back: No, הני מילי היכא דאפקרינהו. hani
milei heicha de'afkirinu. If you... if you made it הפקר, hefker, you
ownerless the water or the... or the stone or the knife or
whatever, then it's a בור bor and then you're exempt on vessels.
אבל היכא דלא אפקרינהו, Aval heicha delo afkirinu, if you did not
make it ownerless, ממונו הוא. mamono hu. Then it is... it's still
your money and it's a type of a שור. shor. Okay, so
רב Rav says you're חייב chayav for damaging the guy's shirt, and
שמואל Shmuel says that you're פטור pattur for damaging the guy's shirt.
Now one minute. If שמואל Shmuel says you're פטור patur for damaging
the guy's shirt, it's a type of a בור, bor, the only
thing that you're left with here to be חייב chayav. for is
what, according to שמואל? Shmuel? So you slipped on the water, the
water is a בור, bor, you're... you're exempt for any water damage
it did to his shirt, so what are you חייב chayav. for?
What does the משנה mishnah say you're חייב chayav for? What type
of damage?
To the person, right? So שמואל Shmuel says it's a double argument.
שמואל Shmuel says this is a בור bor even though you own
it, it's a בור. bor. And therefore he has to explain the
משנה mishnah that you're חייב chayav when the guy hit the ground.
So שמואל Shmuel says even if the בור bor causes you to
trip, but the damage occurred on the ground, not with the water
itself, you're still going to be חייב. chayav So there's a double
debate, right? רב Rav says,
רב Rav says this is a שור. shor. רב Rav says this
is a שור shor and שמואל Shmuel says this is a בור.
bor. And then because רב Rav. says it's a שור, shor, here
he says you're going to be for the guy who hit the
ground, he's going to say you're פטור patur because it's קרקע עולם,
karka olam, קרקע
עולם karka olam whatever. And שמואל Shmuel is going to say you're
going to be חייב. chayav. Okay, so how do you treat the
thing? A שור shor or a בור? bor? And רב Rav who
says it's a שור shor says you're חייב chayav for the clothes,
so you're פטור patur for the person. שמואל Shmuel who says it's
a בור bor says you're פטור patur for the clothes and you're
going to be חייב chayav for the damage to the person even
though he hit himself outside of the object itself. Alright, let's just
finish up here. Let's
read, actually we can't just read two more, just a few more
sentences quickly. So okay, מתיב רב הושעיא: Mativ Rav Hoshaya: ונפל שמה
שור או חמור? venafal shama shor o chamor? שור ולא אדם Shor
v'lo adam חמור ולא כלים. chamor v'lo kelim. מכאן אמרו, Mikan amru,
נפל לתוכו שור וכלים ונשתברו, nafal letocho shor vekelim venishtabru, חמור וכלים
ונתקרעו, chamor vekelim venitkaru, חייב על הבהמה chayav al habehema ופטור על
הכלים. upatur al hakelim.
So the גמרא says, I'm sorry the ברייתא baraita continues, הא למה
זה דומה? Ha lema ze domeh? לאבנו סכינו ומשאו
שהניחם ברשות הרבים והזיקו. L'avno sakino umasa'o shehinicham b'reshut harabim vehiziku. So
the גמרא says, אדרבה, aderaba, מה דומה לזה
מיבעי ליה. ma domeh l'ze mibaei lei.
It's not like a pit is like a rock and a knife.
The pit is the case in the תורה. Torah. It's that the
rock and the knife are like the pit. So the גמרא says
fine, אלא מאי דומה לזה? ela mai domeh l'ze? What would be
similar to the case of the pit? אבנו וסכינו ומשאו שהניחם ברשות
הרבים והזיקו, Avno v'sakino umasa'o shehinicham b'reshut harabim vehiziku,
a stone or a knife that was left in רשות הרבים reshut
harabim and did damage. ולפיכך, Ulefichach, okay, so those are cases of
בור. bor. ולפיכך אם הטיח צלוחיתו באבן חייב, Ulefichach im hitiach tzluchito
b'even chayav,
if you broke your vessels on a rock that somebody left in
רשות הרבים, reshut harabim, then the person is חייב chayav, for the
damage. Now that's strange because we said it was a בור bor
and we said a בור bor is פטור patur. by vessels and
now we said if it got damaged on the rock you're going
to be חייב. chayav So the גמרא says, רישא קשיא לרב. Reisha
kashya l'Rav. The beginning is difficult to רב. Rav Why? Because the
beginning said that the stone and the knife or whatever is a
type of a בור. bor. And רב Rav, would say it's a
שור. shor. Okay, וסיפא קשיא לשמואל, v'seifa kashya l'Shmuel, but the end
is difficult to שמואל Shmuel because the end says that you're חייב
chayav. when the thing breaks on the rock even though שמואל Shmuel
would say that that's a בור bor and you should be פטור.
patur So the גמרא says, ולטעמיך תיקשי לך היא גופא. Uleta'ameicha tikshi
lach hi gufa. The thing is itself contradictory. רישא פטור וסיפא חייב.
Reisha patur v'seifa chayav.
The beginning it sounds like it's a בור, bor, this rock, and
you should be פטור patur, on vessels. And the end says that
you're חייב chayav on vessels with the rock. So the ברייתא's baraita
a real problem. אלא רב מתרץ לטעמיה ושמואל מתרץ לטעמיה. Ela Rav
metaretz l'ta'amei v'Shmuel metaretz l'ta'amei.
Each one explains it their way. רב's Rav read is going to
be the better one. רב מתרץ לטעמיה: Rav metaretz l'ta'amei: במה דברים
אמורים, Bameh devarim amurim, when is your stone, your rock or your
knife or your bag a בור? bor? When it's כשהפקירן, keshehikpiran, when
you were מפקיר mafkir them. אבל לא הפקירן, Aval lo hikpiran, if
you retained ownership, חייב, chayav then it's going to be a שור
shor and you'll be חייב chayav for vessels. לפיכך אם הטיח צלוחיתו
באבן חייב, Lefichach im hitiach tzluchito b'even chayav, therefore if it breaks
on a stone that you weren't מפקיר, mafkir, you're חייב. chayav So
רב, Rav it's easy. Half the ברייתא baraita could be the בור,
bor, right, when you did מפקיר mafkir it, and that's when it
compares it to a בור. bor. And when it says you're חייב
chayav for vessels, that's a שור shor when you retained ownership. Okay,
ושמואל מתרץ לטעמיה, Ushmuel metaretz l'ta'amei, שמואל Shmuel explains according to his
reasoning: השתא דאמרת אבנו סכינו ומשאו כבור דמי, Hashta d'amart avno sakino
umasa'o k'bor dami,
now that we said אבנו סכינו ומשאו avno sakino umasa'o is like
a בור bor whether you own it or don't own it, רבי
יהודה דמחייב על נזקי כלים בבור, Rabbi Yehuda d'mechayev al nizkei kelim
b'bor, for רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that says there's a position of
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that says that a בור bor you do
pay for breaking vessels. לפיכך הטיח צלוחיתו באבן חייב, Lefichach hitiach tzluchito
b'even chayav, then you'd be חייב chayav. if your stuff broke on
a rock. It's a very bad read. It's saying like, oh by
the way, if you're חייב chayav for vessels, you're חייב chayav for
vessels. You know, it has nothing to do with the special case
of it being the rock. Okay, but anyway we have a ברייתא
baraita here that basically we have the debate of, there's two debates
of רב Rav and שמואל. Shmuel. One is the very interesting thing
if you are pushed by a שור shor or trip over a
בור bor and injure yourself on the ground are you חייב chayav
or not? רב Rav says you're פטור, שמואל Shmuel says you're חייב.
chayav But the earlier debate is what is the nature of this
water or the stone or the rock that you still own? רב
Rav says it's a שור shor and therefore you could be חייב
chayav for damage to the vessel. And שמואל, Shmuel, I'm sorry, רב
says it's a שור Shor and therefore you can be חייב for
damage to the clothes and damage to the vessels, and שמואל Shmuel
says it's a בור. Bor. And that then obviously forces them to
interpret the משנה Mishna in a particular way. And we end with
this ברייתא braita here, or this last ברייתא braita we saw, seems
to say both, seems to say it's a בור Bor and then
you're חייב with vessels. So רב says it's a בור Bor when
you don't own it, it's a שור Shor when you do own
it. שמואל Shmuel says it's always a בור Bor and the stuff
that says at the end that you're חייב for vessels is a
position that you're חייב for vessels in a בור, Bor, okay, but
that's obviously a harder read in the ברייתא. braita. All right, we
will end with this.